<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>England and Scotland united, disjoyned. Or, A gentle corosive, and healing plaister, applied to two dying kingdoms: with some balsamum for wounded Ireland; humbly presented to both kingdoms, and communicated to all good subjects, that wish peace and good to the kingdoms, or to either of them. Wherein is represented, the grievances of the people, and their several murmurings. By Ethog Grimes Gent.</title>
            <author>Smith, George, 1602 or 3-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93345</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4034</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E447_30</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863494</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863494</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161820</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93345)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161820)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 71:E447[30])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>England and Scotland united, disjoyned. Or, A gentle corosive, and healing plaister, applied to two dying kingdoms: with some balsamum for wounded Ireland; humbly presented to both kingdoms, and communicated to all good subjects, that wish peace and good to the kingdoms, or to either of them. Wherein is represented, the grievances of the people, and their several murmurings. By Ethog Grimes Gent.</title>
                  <author>Smith, George, 1602 or 3-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Laurence Chapman, and are to be sold at his shop, next door to the Fountain Tavern in the Strand, near the Savoy,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Ethog Grimes is an anagram of George Smith.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 16".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Foreign relations --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Foreign relations --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161820:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENGLAND AND SCOTLAND UNITED, DISJOYNED.</p>
            <p>OR, A gentle <hi>Coroſive,</hi> and healing Plaiſter, applied to two dying KINGDOMS: WITH Some <hi>Balſamum</hi> for wounded <hi>Ireland;</hi> HUMBLY Preſented to both Kingdoms, and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to all good Subjects, that wiſh Peace and good to the Kingdoms, or to either of them.</p>
            <p>Wherein is repreſented, The Grievances of the <hi>PEOPLE,</hi> and their ſeveral Murmurings.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Ethog Grimes</hi> Gent.</p>
            <q>Read before you judge: Read all or read none.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Sam. 2 16.</hi>
               </bibl> Then Abner called to Joab, and ſaid, shall the ſword devour for ever? Knoweſt thou not that it will be bitterneſs in the latter end? How long ſhall it be then, ere thou bid the people retur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from following their brethren?</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 1 5.</hi>
               </bibl> Why ſhould ye be ſmitten any more? ye will revolt more and more: the whole head is ſick, and the heart is faint.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ier. 8. 22</hi>
               </bibl> Is there no balm in Gilead? Is there no phyſician there? Why then is not the daughter of my people recovered?</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Laurence Chapman,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p, next door to the Fountain Tavern in the Strand, near the Savoy. 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:161820:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:161820:2"/>
            <head>England and Scotland United, Disjoyned: OR, A gentle Coroſive, and healing Plaiſter, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to two dying Kingdoms: WITH Some Balſamum for wounded <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y your leave Gentlemen, give me leave to ſtep in among you, and excuſe my boldneſs, I have a little intereſt with you in the Kingdom, as well as you, which I would not loſe, nor do I know how to ſave; deem me not an intruder, though I crowd in, I truly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I ſcarce know where I am, things are ſo promiſcouſly ſhuffled together, men and things are ſo metamorphoſed; men know not themſelves, nor their own, the world ſeems as it were turned round, or in confuſion: Law is changed into Looſneſs, and Liberty into Licentiouſneſs, where Order was, there is Confuſion, and Fancy or Will, is come in the place of Conſcience; Conſcience is ſhrank or ſeared with an hot iron, or hath quite ſuffered ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack; ſacred Truth analized, judged, miſinterpreted, eclipſed, and comdemned by Humane Reaſon, men and things all out of their places; conquering <hi>Mars</hi> threatens the Iſlands with new War, <hi>Jupiter</hi> caſts ill aſpects on men and things, love is departed from men, and malignity of ſpirit increaſeth, horrid Pride, Ambition and Covetouſneſs, have contracted deſtructive diviſions, in King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, Cities, Societies and Families, <hi>The ſon diſhonoreth the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Micah 7. 6.</note> 
               <hi>father,</hi> the brother is againſt the brother, <hi>&amp;c. and a mans ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161820:3"/> are the men of his own houſe:</hi> is Chriſt a Prophet? then conclude, <hi>a Kingdom, a City, a Houſe ſo divided cannot ſtand.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mark 3 24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>What's the matter? is all the world grown mad? the effects ſhew the cauſe, are not <hi>Englands</hi> brainſick diſtempers, conceited fancies, unparalleld head-ſtrong paſſions, and unreaſonable acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the effects of the inflammation of the brain to madneſs? What Bedlam fantacies, whimzeys, and ſelf-fooling affections are diſcovered in men, raging in all Societies and Families? vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence overſpreads all, as if there were new <hi>Nimrods</hi> on the earth, or as if the people were building new <hi>Babels;</hi> Midſummer-moon hath been apparently operative all this year: What influence the Moon, the Planets, or Comets have upon mens bodies or fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, I know not; nor did ever regard, no more then ſome old new Propheſies lately diſcovered, which I heed as Necroman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers predictions.</p>
            <p>But I cannot tell what to think, that <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> are made friends, and yet love not one another, that <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs</hi> ſhould be in conjunction with <hi>Venus,</hi> and <hi>Veſta</hi> forſake her chaſtity; is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty a fool? <hi>Minerva</hi> and <hi>Pall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce</hi> were wiſe, how is it they uſurp <hi>Meneſis</hi> and ſeek their own revenge? it's ſtrange to me, and is no leſs then madneſs; or is it a myſtery? but whether madneſs, or myſtery, thoſe are ſymptomes of Mortal-ſickneſs in a Kingdom, and at this time predict a period to three kingdoms, all lying at this day upon the bed of languiſhing, tortured with the pain of theſe diſtempers, and the infected members of each, are worſe then <hi>Solomons</hi> mad-man, <hi>Who</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>caſt firebrands, arrows</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 15. 18.</note> 
               <hi>and death:</hi> It is mad-mens paſtime to do miſchief, they care not who they hurt, whether themſelves or others, ſo they fulfil their phrantick fancies; a few ſuch mad-men may deſtroy all: But if all ſhall be mad, who ſhall prevent deſtruction? it was a curſe threatned upon the rebellious <hi>Jews</hi> (and is verified in truth upon <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland) The Lord ſhall ſmite thee with madneſs, and blindeneſs, and aſtoniſhment of heart, and thou ſhalt be mad for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u. 28 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 34.</note> 
               <hi>the ſight of thine eyes, that thou ſhalt ſee, &amp;c.</hi> Self-pride, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, Covetouſneſs, and extream Oppreſſion, have put three Kingdoms into an extream mad condition: Oppreſsion (ſaith the Wiſe man) makes a wiſe man mad; the heart of the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer is mad in oppreſſing, the ſweet of gain hath deſtroyed his heart,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:161820:3"/> though otherwiſe a wiſe man, and like the horſeleech he cryes, <hi>Give, give:</hi> On the other ſide the oppreſſed, under the burthen of preſſures lying long upon him, forgets his wiſdom, and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and grows into deſperation, ſtark mad, throws himſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any danger, counts it the ſmalleſt hazard (in way of revenge) <note place="margin">Vid. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. lib. 1 cap. 12. ult.</note> to venture his life in every attempt, counting himſelf deprived of the benefit of it, whileſt wounded by galling preſſures: Ill cauſes we know too often produce worſe effects.</p>
            <p>No man is born for himſelf, but for others good as his own, not for the hurt of any: We ought to do good to every man, but much more to ſeek to do good, by laying out our ſelves for the publick Weal; and in caſes of neceſſity to the uttermoſt of our ability, without grudging, elſe were men ingrate to God, and betrayers of the Commonweal. But when Princes, or Magiſtrates, ſhall extort treaſure from a willing and free people, and convert their publick moneys to private uſes, ſelf-purpoſes, to particular ends, it cannot be well endured, eſpecially when accounts of ſuch moneys are not made to the Kingdom: This kindles a fire of jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, and makes men cry againſt it, as grinding oppreſſion, and Robbing the Commonweal It was a reproof againſt the houſe of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and the Princes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> That <hi>they built up Zion with</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mic. 3. 10</note> 
               <hi>blood, and Jeruſalem with iniquity;</hi> not onely killing by the ſword is counted bloody (of which <hi>England</hi> ſtand guilty) but when <hi>The</hi> 
               <note place="margin">ve. 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>Heads of the people ſhall judge for reward, and the Prieſts teach for hire, the Prophets divine for money, yet lean upon the Lord and ſay, Is not the Lord among us, none evil can come to us:</hi> conſider what follows, <hi>Therefore ſhall Zion for your ſake be plowed as a field, and Jeruſalem ſhall become heaps,</hi> &amp;c. likeneſs in ſin, brings likeneſs of judgement.</p>
            <p>You ſhall ſee that becauſe the two ſons of <hi>Samuel</hi> that judged <hi>Iſrael</hi> were not juſt in all the ways of their father, <hi>but turned aſide after lucre, took bribes, and perverted judgement,</hi> all the Elders of <hi>Iſrael</hi> gathered themſelves together, and came to <hi>Samuel,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Make us a king to judge us, like other nations:</hi> the thing <note place="margin">1 Sa. 8. 3.</note> diſpleaſed <hi>Samuel,</hi> and was a ſin againſt God; Why? not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that they deſired a King, that was not a ſin, but becauſe in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, with revenge againſt <hi>Samuel</hi> and his ſons, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected the government that God had ſet over them, therefore the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:161820:4"/> Lord ſaith, <hi>They have not rejected thee, but they have rejected me:</hi> Doubtleſs <hi>David</hi> ſhould have been their King, though they had not <note place="margin">Vpon this ground the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my is not ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifiable in their diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp;c. Rom 12. 19.</note> asked a King, their ſin was, that they would not ſtay Gods time: Private perſons may not caſt reproaches, nor calumniate the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, nor perſons of the Magiſtrate, nor of the Miniſtery, nor prejudge Counſels, nor Actions, much leſs riſe in Arms againſt them, but make humble addreſs, and pray unto God, and wait Gods time for redreſs of ſuch evils, <hi>Vengeance is mine</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>and I will repay it,</hi> &amp;c. obedience is better then ſacrifice, <hi>And rebellion is as the ſin of witchcraft:</hi> Although the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate fail in his duty toward the people (ſaith judicious <hi>Calvin)</hi> the people may not tranſgreſs in their duty to the Magiſtrate, but pray unto God for his or their amendment and converſion, and amend their own faults, conſidering, that God often puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſins of a people by corrupt Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>It may be ſome will object, that if this be good Divinity, we the people of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Stotland</hi> ought not to have taken up arms againſt the Kings Authority, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, We did it not as private men, but by Authority; therefore I ſay with Mr. <hi>Calvin, There is a time when God will raiſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Sam 15. 22. <hi>Cilv.</hi> in <hi>inſtitut. lib. 4. cap. 20 ſect.</hi> 30.</note> 
               <hi>up open revengers of the unjuſt Government of Princes and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, ſuch as he will arm with authority &amp; command from himſelf,</hi> like as God ſtirred up <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> to deliver <hi>Iſrael</hi> from the bondage in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and ſeveral deliverers at ſundry times to free his people from their ſeveral preſſures, as <hi>Ehud, Barak, Deborah, Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon, Sampſon, Jepththah,</hi> and others mentioned in the book of <hi>Judges;</hi> and ſuch a deliverance God raiſed up to his people of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> when he by his providence eſtabliſhed this Parliament, at ſuch a time when we thought our ſelves paſt hope; We know it was contrary to the deſign of His Majeſties Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel then acting, and we know it was not in our power to do it without the King, therefore it was of God onely, who ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Kings heart, and infatuated His evil Counſel, that the King did it by His own Act, according to the Law of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the Rights of the Subject, and in which the King is ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually preſent, though perſonally abſent; we know alſo, that His Majeſty paſſed ſeveral Acts of grace, for which we did, and do honor, and thank Him, but have no reaſon to thank that evil
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:161820:4"/> Counſel, who intended thereby onely to ſweeten the people, and ſteal away their affections to joyn in a war (being ſo deceived) to diſſolve the Parliament, and Null all that they would, <hi>But</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob 5. 12.</note> 
               <hi>God diſappointed the devices of the crafty ſo that their hands cannot perform their enterprize.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again divine <hi>Calvin,</hi> the great ſupporter of Magiſtracy, and the Authority of Princes, the moſt earneſt preſſer to obedience, ſaith thus of Parliaments (being once called) <hi>If they</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall wink at Kings wilful raging over, and treading down the poor</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Calv. inſtitut.</hi> lib. 4. cap. 20. ſect. 31.</note> 
               <hi>Commonalty, it is a breach of Faith in them, becauſe they deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully betray the Liberty of the people, whereof they are protectors by the Ordinance of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>While <hi>Iſrael</hi> lay under the ſore preſſures and bondage of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raohs</hi> taskmaſters in <hi>Egypt,</hi> they groaned under their heavy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, as inſupportable, and cryed unto God, God raiſed up <hi>Moſes</hi> their deliverer; but quickly they forgot the bitterneſs of that bondage, and meeting with ſome momentary hardſhip in the way through the Wilderneſs, to the Land of reſt and peace, (which way God brought them to <hi>humble them, &amp; to prove them:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut 8. 2 verſe 16.</note> and that <hi>he might do them good in the latter end)</hi> they grew impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, murmured, and rebelled againſt God, and againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> that led them, notwithſtanding they had been ſpectators of Gods Almighty power, wonders, and outſtretched arm againſt the Egyptians, for their deliverance, and ſang praiſes unto God, <hi>that had triumphed gloriouſly, and thrown the horſe and his rider in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 15. 1.</note> 
               <hi>the Red-ſea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider, I pray, can it be well with us of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> or with our great City <hi>London,</hi> or mutinous Counties, if we ſhall parallel the Murmurings and Rebellions of rebellious <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Can you, or either of you, forget how you have groaned under the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of an unlimited Prerogative, even whil'ſt it was but in the infancy of it? Can ye forget how your Laws were ſtretcht upon the tenters of Prerogative, till they were thin, and weak as ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders webs, and ſerved onely as ſnares and nets to catch ſmall flies, through which ſtinging hornets, and hurtful waſps, brake at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; your Parliaments were broken in pieces, diſgraced, rejected, made uſeleſs, as having no conſiſtence with lawles Prerogative, you know how the ill Counſel of thoſe times bought and ſold Juſtice,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:161820:5"/> Judges were diſplaced for doing juſtly, and for refuſing to do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly: They were made to buy their places dear, and ſuffered to ſell their ſervice dearer, that they might be gainers; No Bribe, no Juſtice; and the greateſt Bribe, or beſt Friend, moſt times prevailed, whether juſt or unjuſt: mens Eſtates were forced by illegal Taxes, Loans, Knight-money, Forreſt-lands, Timber, Woods, Buildings, Compoſitions for Cottages, Coat and Conduct-money, &amp;c. alſo extream Taxes by Cuſtoms, Tunnage and Poundage, Ship-money, and infinite Monopolies of all ſorts of Commodities, to the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of Trade, Commerce and Traffick, and ruine of ſeveral eſtabliſhed Corporations, the whole Kingdom (as well as <hi>London)</hi> was ſenſible of the miſery, and groaned under the burthen: What Tradeſman in the great City (Maſter or Apprentice) in thoſe times, cryed not out (in a feeling ſence) that they ſhould be all undone? many thouſands complained they were deprived of their Livelyhoods, and of their Trades for which they ſerved, all looking upon thoſe burthens as remedileſs, all Gunpowder, and Arms of defence was at that time denyed to the Subject, Bands of Soldiers were billeted upon the Kingdom in moſt of the great Towns, and ſome Villages, Horſes and their Riders were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted for, and coming from beyond ſea; What to do? but to awe the Kingdom, and to enſlave Poſterity, no Forrain was then either envading nor threatning us: How many of our gallant fideal Gentlemen were drawn by pretences to the Iſle of <hi>Ree,</hi> and to <hi>Cardiſe,</hi> there loſt, betrayed and murthered; ſhips lent and ſold to ſerve againſt the Proteſtants of <hi>France,</hi> the Town of <hi>Rochel</hi> and other places loſt, all means uſed to weaken us at home, and the Proteſtants in other Countreys, all done to give way to Popery.</p>
            <p>Nor can our Brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> forget, how a new old Maſs Liturgy was forced upon them, ſuch as was contrived at <hi>Rome,</hi> prepared by the arch Enemy <hi>Canterbury,</hi> which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing, were threatned by an Army; a Parliament in <hi>England</hi> was called to raiſe money to engage in a War with <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament refuſed to contribute in that War, and was preſently diſmiſſed, yet an Army was raiſed, and <hi>Scotland</hi> in their defence brought their Army into <hi>England;</hi> how much they were engaged to <hi>England,</hi> for their brotherly love, and good
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:161820:5"/> affections (the people generally refuſing to contribute any thing to hurt them) they cannot but remember; nor can they forget what humble ſupplicants and petitioners the Lords and Gentlemen of all Counties of <hi>England</hi> were in their behalf, which I hope ſhall never be repaid by any ill from that Kingdom: I would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minde them of theſe things.</p>
            <p>Let me again put <hi>England</hi> in minde of the Plots and Deſigns of the Hierarchy, to corrupt our Religion by Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and prophaneneſs, you had Canons, Articles and Lyturgies, given you as gilded pills, to purge out ſound Doctrine: And to plant prophaneneſs, a Book was commanded to be read in all Churches, to give liberty to prophane the holy Sabbath, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding afternoon Sermons; and there was injunctions penal to keep holy Popiſh Saints days, all Church-ſervice was adulterated: In a word, Religion was choaked with the lawn of Heirarchy, the mouthes of godly Miniſters ſtopped, their perſons perſecuted, impriſoned, baniſhed (Biſhop <hi>Wren</hi> will not deny it) as it was with <hi>Jeremiah</hi> and <hi>Baruch</hi> in the days of <hi>Jehoiakim,</hi> and with <hi>Micaiah</hi> in the time of <hi>Ahab,</hi> ſo was it unto them, becauſe they ſpake the word of God to the people, and ſaid, Go not up to <hi>Ramath-Gilead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Good men were alſo cauterized, pillory'd, and ſtigmatized for like cauſes; and who knows but the Proteſtants in <hi>England</hi> ſhould intentionally have acted the firſt ſcene in that Bloody Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy that <hi>Ireland</hi> hath done; it was not that the common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my had greater love, or more pity to us, but Gods mercy to us; And ſhall we now deſtroy one another?</p>
            <p>Conſider how we cryed out in thoſe times for a Parliament, a Parliament, a Parliament, ſaying, Nothing but a Parliament could deliver us, and keep our poſterities from bondage; God gave us a Parliament, and made our Parliament a bleſſing to us, till we idolized them; and now becauſe we finde they are not Gods, but men, and men of infirmities, you cry out againſt Parliaments, and calumniate them, ready to ſtone them: O ungrateful people! be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God tryeth you, as he did the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the wilderneſs, to humble you, and will not ſuffer the Parliament to eſtabliſh your peace, ſo ſoon as you deſire, you will like the Jews murmure, and ſin againſt God, notwithſtrnding God hath done very great and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:161820:6"/> miraculous things for you: Why do you luſt and look back to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, and ſay as the Idolatrous Iſraelites, <hi>It had been better for us</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 14. 12.</note> 
               <hi>to ſerve the Egyptians, then to dye in the wilderneſs;</hi> you would eat the ſweet, but you will not endure to taſte of the ſowre; you would have your ſore healed, but will not endure the plaiſter; you ſay many Members in Parliament are ſelf-ſeekers, not minding the common good; I pray who ſent them thither? If you were fools in your choyce, your backs muſt bear the fools reward: will you therefore deſtroy Parliaments, and make your poſterity-Slaves? wil nothing ſatisfie you now but a King, &amp; a King upon any terms? Truly, I wiſh and pray that we may have a King, and a bleſſing with him, But why do ye cry out as ye do, A King upon any terms? Is this leſs then madneſs in you? you have forgot the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of Egypt, and think onely upon the fleſh-pots, onions and garlick, &amp;c. O ſilly men! why do ye break your Covenant with God and men? Take heed ye be not like Iſrael in ſin, leſt ye be like Iſrael in puniſhment; they murmured and were diſobedient to God, but therefore they were deſtroyed by <hi>the ſword of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Num. 14. 37.</note> 
               <hi>by the Peſtilence, by Serpents; Korah</hi> and his company were ſwallowed up by the earth: conſider that the Apoſtle tells you and me, even all us at this day, that <hi>All thoſe things</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 11.</note> 
               <hi>hapned for our enſamples, and are written for our admonition, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom the ends of the world are come.</hi> Now we know that the many thouſands that came out of Egypt, dyed all in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, except <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Caleb,</hi> and their little ones that were born in <note place="margin">Num. 14. 34. 35.</note> the deſert: Let not us flatter our ſelves, to think though we do the ſame things, that we ſhal eſcape; but let us be admoniſhed &amp; do our duties in all obedience, that it may be wel with us in the later end.</p>
            <p>I blame none ſimply for deſiring a King, nor for petitioning for a Treaty with the King; for I wiſh honor to his perſon, and bliſs to his ſoul, and ſo ſhall ever pray: But I cannot Idolize any King; Kings are but men, and all men have failings; what hath been, may be again, the burnt childe dreads the fire; and men once deceived, truſt not again without aſſurance: Though Kings cannot erre, their Councels have erred, and for ought we know, will erre again; firſt let the Kingdom have its rights, which Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Law hath given to free Subjects, then make the King as great as he can be, that his Honor and juſt Greatneſs may be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:161820:6"/> ever ſplendant in Juſtice and Clemency: God forbid, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (through evil Counſel) he hath erred, and infringed the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Liberty, that therefore we his Subjects ſhould utterly caſt him off, or take from him or his poſterity any of his or their Rights: I hope none will ſay, that becauſe his Majeſties Councel (put on by <hi>Romes</hi> Hierarchy) hath cauſed a War, that we will have no more a Peace. We know our War was to defend Priviledges of Parliament, our Liberties and Religion (all which are involved in Parliaments) not to deſtroy the King, nor his poſterity.</p>
            <p>But it highly concerns us to take heed what peace is made, and how; for there is a deſtructive peace, as there is a depopulating war: And herein we have made our reſpective Members in free Parliament, our Judge; and ſo long as a free Parliament, and of free Election, we are not to judge their actions, but are bound to maintain their Freedom and Priviledge, for therein ſtands our Peace and welfare to our poſterities; you know what <hi>Jehu</hi> ſaid to <hi>Joram</hi> when he asked if it were peace, <hi>What peace,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 King. 9. 22.</note> 
               <hi>ſo long as the Whoredoms of thy mother Jezebel, and her witchcrafts are ſo many? There is no peace ſaith the Lord unto the wicked:</hi> Will <note place="margin">Iſa. 48. 22.</note> God give peace to a wicked Nation, when blood and oppreſſion, and horrible hypocriſie cryeth for vengeance, and for deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? <hi>Blood hath defiled the Land, and the Land cannot be cleanſed of the blood that is ſhed, but by the blood of them that ſhed it:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Num. 35. 33.</note> God is ſurely making inquiſition for blood, and for injuſtice, as well in Subjects as Princes; if therefore God will make <hi>his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows drunk with blood, from the beginning of revenges upon his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32. 42.</note> 
               <hi>Enemies, who can withſtand it? We have looked for peace, but no good came: and for a time of health, but behold trouble: For</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier 8. 15.</note> 
               <hi>ſpoilers and robbers are come upon us, and the ſword of the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth from one end of the Land to the other:</hi> Therefore we muſt ſeek God, repent of our blood guiltineſs and ſecret robbery, our hypocriſie, and our idolatry, and purge the Land of polutions, and erroneous damnable Doctrines, or God will <hi>cut off both branch and ruſh in one day; policy and craft may proſper in a mans hand,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dan. 8. 25.</note> 
               <hi>and he may magnifie himſelf in his heart, and by peace deſtroy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; but he ſhall be broken without hand:</hi> We like <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> have not known the <hi>things that belong to our peace, and they now ſeem to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk 19. 42.</note> 
               <hi>be hid from our eyes:</hi> but whileſt there is life, there is hope, let us
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:161820:7"/> therefore repent and do our firſt works, leſt we, like <hi>Judea</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> be deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>Why are we divided in our judgements, and in our practiſes? ſome cry out for the King, and peace upon any terms; other ſay, Not the King, becauſe he hath againſt the Law and his Oath, broken his truſt, by which three Kingdoms are imbrewed in their bloods. <hi>Peter de la Primanday</hi> in his Accademy (who was <note place="margin">French Accadem. par. 1. cap. 39.</note> Chancellor and Steward of the French Kings houſe) ſaith, <hi>No fault is more deteſtable in a Prince then Perjury, for if he that is debtor and pledge for juſtice be diſloyal, there is no more truſt to be given to him in all his Oaths, but if he be upright, his bare word ought to be to him for a Law: God himſelf</hi> (ſaith the Maſter of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences) <hi>is bound by his promiſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now conſider, what anſwer his Majeſty ſent to the Houſe of Commons, 31 <hi>Dec.</hi> 1641. to their deſires as touching a Guard; promiſing <hi>by the word of a King, that the ſecurity of them, and every one of them, was and ſhould be as much his care, as the preſervation of himſelf and children:</hi> Yet by the influence of evil Councellors on Tueſday the 4 of <hi>January,</hi> 1641. but four days following, (as by the Declaration of the Houſe appears, touching the breach of priviledge of Parliament) a perſonal force was made upon the Houſe by about Five hundred Armed men, who, if his Majeſties clemency (through Gods providence in that particular) had not tranſcended their mercy, they had (as ſome of them then ſaid) cut <note place="margin">See the Declar. of the Houſe of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons touching the breach of Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>Jan.</hi> 17. 1641. See De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar. of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons 11 <hi>Feb.</hi> 1647.</note> all the throats of the Members of the houſe of Commons: we know alſo that the Pacification concluded between the King and our Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> was by His evil Councel made <hi>Null</hi> after he came to Court: Proteſtations and Vows have been made, That no conſent ſhould ever be given to the toleration of Popery, nor to the aboliſhing of any Statute made againſt Papiſts; yet it is too evident, that evil Counſel prevailed, ſo as His Majeſty under His own Hand promiſeth the Queen and the Earl of <hi>Ormond,</hi> to take away all penal Laws made againſt Papiſts in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> Many other things of breach of promiſe might be inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, which I take no delight to divulge; <hi>Mercy and truth</hi> (ſaith the wiſeſt of Kings) <hi>preſerves the King, and is the upholding of his Throne.</hi> It was a good ſaying of <hi>Seneca</hi> to <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ro Ceſar, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Right and Juſtice commands to ſpare Captives, and ſuch as
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:161820:7"/> are bought with money to be Slaves, are to be juſtly dealt with;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seneca</hi> of clemency l. 1. c. 18.</note> 
               <hi>much more juſt is it for thee</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>not to abuſe free-men, inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous and honeſt, but to entertain them as under thy Government, to defend them as Subjects, &amp;c.</hi> In the next Chapter he draws an inference from the King of Bees, who hath no ſting, ſaying, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath denied it, becauſe he ſhould not be cruel, nor ſeek re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge; he ſaith further, That <hi>Clemency will ſecure a King in the open field, and his impregnable Fortreſs is the love of his Subjects,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seneca</hi> of clemency l. 1. c. 19.</note> 
               <hi>when he ſo behaves himſelf, as that the Commonwealth is not his, but he the Commonwealths.</hi> The mutual love between Princes and people, is the upholding of a Commonweal: Well ſaith <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi> to <hi>Nero,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>The King in ſafety, all men live in peace,</l>
                  <l>The King once loſt, then Faith and Truth doth ceaſe.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Others there are like Lords of the firſt head, that cry, No King at all, but Kingly Subjects; but theſe men know not of what Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits they are: Let theſe men examine themſelves, whats be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of Conſcience, of Charity, and of their Engagement by Covenant, which bindes ſo to accept of the King with honor and ſafety, ſo far as we may do it with ſecurity and preſervation of our Laws and Religion.</p>
            <p>Yet let not men be ſo eager of a King, and of peace, but upon good terms, for God may <hi>give us a King in his anger, and take</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hoſ 13. 11.</note> 
               <hi>him away in his diſpleaſure;</hi> let us hold truth with us, though we loſe all beſides, and not be like prophane <hi>Eſau, Who ſold his Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right</hi> 
               <note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 11. 16.</note> 
               <hi>for one morſel of meat;</hi> nor like the <hi>Gadarens</hi> that would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part with Chriſt, then their ſwine: The mad multitude ſeem like him whoſe abode was among the tombs, could not be reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor bound with chains from violence; conſider the ſaying of the Prophet, <hi>If ye be willing and obedient, ye ſhall eat the good of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1. 19. 20.</note> 
               <hi>the Land, but if ye refuſe and rebel, ye ſhall be devoured by the ſword, for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know your allegations againſt the preſent evils, are in effect what you complained of under prerogative power <hi>(viz.)</hi> Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and Illegal power uſed over you, your money exhauſted, divided, and given to private purſes, Receivers, Collectors, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees, Souldiers <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not brought to ſtrict Accompt for the vaſt ſums received, a ſupernumerous Army maintained by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:161820:8"/> Taxes and Free-quarter, guiltleſs men accuſed, and guilty men not queſtioned, Faction and Self-intereſt preferred, publike peace and ſafety neglected, Law and Covenant wreſted, Religion diſcountenanced, Miniſters contemned, Schiſms, Hereſie and Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemy cheriſhed (at leaſt connived at) publique prejudice done by protections, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all which (you ſay) could not be born with in a King, therefore cannot be endured by any Subject; from all which you hoped a Parliament would have freed you, but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy is worſe then the diſeaſe, and your preſſures increaſed: All great Offices of profit in the Commonweal, are ingroſſed into particular mens hands (whoſe ſervice and attendance ought to be imployed to publique benefit) which if executed by private men (reaſonable ſallery being allowed them) who have loſt their whole livelihoods by the Enemy, for their fidelity to the Parliament, would in overplus much benefit the Commonweal, have paid poor windows, mained Soldiers, and much Arrears, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but (as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaith in another caſe) <hi>This is a people robbed and ſpoiled, they</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa 42. 22.</note> 
               <hi>are all of them ſnared in holes, and they are hid in Priſon-houſes, they are for a prey, and none delivereth, for a ſpoil, and none ſaith, Reſtore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, the people are brought into jealouſie of a ruling over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awing Army, as it were forcing a Toleration and Liberty to all Sectaries, and their juſt Liberty is infringed, <hi>&amp;c. The Righteous</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Amos 2. 6. Iſa. 13. 14</note> 
               <hi>are ſold for ſilver, and the poor for a pair of ſhooes, therefore the Lord entreth into Judgement with the Ancients of the people, and with the Princes, for they have eaten up the vineyard, and the ſpoil of the poor is in their houſes:</hi> Theſe are your allegations, all which I cannot excuſe, for God and men know many things are not as they ought to be, nor as they might have been; but for what is now under Parliament preſſures, ſome neceſſity may be pleaded; and what was by the Kings evil Councellors, was Wil, and their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary act to enſlave, that would have been for ever, this is but mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary: 'Tis true, the Army in all things are not juſtifiable, they are but men, and have erred as men, in Judgement and practice, but have been, and are happy inſtruments (under God) to ſave us from deſtruction, faithful and victorious, deſerving Honor and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence; let the people forget, and the Army repent, God will forgive and redreſs all grievances: The cauſes and cures I ſhall
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:161820:8"/> give you in the proper place: Firſt give me leave to tell you a Story;</p>
            <p>In the time of <hi>Romulus</hi> King of the <hi>Romans,</hi> he made a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Councellors of the beſt and honeſteſt Noblemen; theſe (when together) were called <hi>Senatus,</hi> to whom there were after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward a greater number added, and called Senators; theſe were Patrons, Helpers, Defendors and Councelors to the People, counted then a ſhame to them to take any Bribe or Reward of the people; this cauſed great love and unity among them, the one were Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, the other were obedient: But <hi>Romulus</hi> growing great and ſucceſsful, began to be Tyrant-like, the Senators did nothing, but were called a Councel for faſhion, not for any Advice or Counſel; for when aſſembled, they onely heard the <hi>Kings</hi> pleaſure and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, and ſo departed: This put them upon a deſire to have a free State, and not to be ſubject only to the rule of a King; ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after <hi>Romulus</hi> making Oration to the people, at a place with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the City, the Sun was ſuddenly darkened, and there was terrible Thunder, flaſhings of Lightenings, and mighty Winds, which ſeperated the people every way one from another, the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators remaining together, in which time <hi>Romulus</hi> vaniſht away, <note place="margin">Plut. <hi>life</hi> Romulus.</note> was no more ſeen alive or dead; when the Storm was paſt and the day cleared, the people asked for the King, the Noblemen wiſht them not to enquire after the King, but to honor and reverence him, for he was taken up into heaven, ſome of the people liked it well, others not ſatisfied, accuſed the Senators of making away the King; after much ado and diſcontent, one of the Noblemen of good eſteem among the people, whom they held for an honeſt man, Arguments and by Oaths affirmed, the King was taken up by the gods into Heaven, to dwell with them, having built that famous City, and that <hi>Romulus</hi> ſhould henceforth be their god, ſo he appeaſed all the people: The people afterwards not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented without a King, cauſed another tumult, about chooſing a King, they being of divers Opinions; the Senators alſo were in ſuſpition one of another, but all agreed of a neceſſity to chooſe a King; and to prevent greater confuſion, the Senators concluded that every one of them ſhould by turns carry the State of a King, ſix hours in a day, and ſix hours at night, the next day another, and ſo in order: ſuſpition ſtill grew in the people, who ſaid, This
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:161820:9"/> was a device to get all Government into a few mens hands: At length to appeaſe all, the people agreed to chooſe <hi>Numa Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilius</hi> a <hi>Sabine,</hi> a man of vertue, and wiſdom, free from tove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs and vice, addicted to divine ſtudy, and the exerciſe of Juſtice: Meſſengers were ſent to <hi>Numa</hi> to entreat him to accept of the Kingdom; he anſwered, the change of a mans life was ever dangerous, and for him that wanted nothing, it was folly to leave a certainty for an uncertainty, caſting many dangers and perils in being a King, with other Allegations of his own unfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Meſſengers beſought him by many Arguments to accept of it, and not give any cauſe of new trouble among the people, ſeeing all had ſo freely choſen him to be their King.</p>
            <p>After long perſwation <hi>Numa</hi> accepted of it, came to <hi>Rome,</hi> the Senate and people flockt to meet him, the women bleſſed him, and ſang to his praiſes, Sacrifice was done for him in the Temples of their gods, and with great joy he was brought to the Market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place, where his Election was Proclaimed, and he choſen by the voyce of all the people. Having received the Royal Seat, he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed the guard of Soldiers that was to guard his perſon, ſaying, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plut.</hi> in life of <hi>Pompil.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He would not miſtruſt thoſe that truſted him, neither would he be King over people that ſhould miſtruſt him.</hi> Then he began to work upon the affections of the people, to draw them from vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent warlike deſires, to quiet life, civility and meekneſs in maners, and to the ſervice of the gods; by which peace was eſtabliſhed at home, and with all Nations, all <hi>Numa</hi>'s days.</p>
            <p>Let men make their own Application; onely obſerve this, That Differences and Commotions have been in all Ages, and under all Governments, whether Monarchical, Ariſtocracy, Democracy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all have been ſubject to Tyrannical Oppreſſion, Injuſtice and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, by Kings, by Senates, and by the People: But certain no Kingdom nor Commonweal in the world, had ever any better Government, for the conſtitution of well regulated Laws, then <hi>England,</hi> by King, Lords and Commons; That there are miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages in this Government, is neglect of Execution, ariſing either from greedy Oppreſſion and Ambition in the ſuperior, or from Pride and Diſobedience in the inferior, both which are the defects of this Age.</p>
            <p>Now I ſhall truly ſhew you the cauſes of all theſe Diſtempers,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:161820:9"/> as they are at this day: We uſe to ſay, the diſeaſe once known, the cure is eaſie, if men will; the firſt cauſe is the Devil, he ſuggeſts evil ſurmiſes, ſuſpitions and jealouſies, leads men into errors, and propounds falſe ends in deſigns, by this we are divided and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded; the Scriptures term him to be an <hi>Adverſary,</hi> a <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter,</hi> and a <hi>Murtherer,</hi> &amp;c. he is ſubtile in tempting, therefore cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Old ſerpent,</hi> the <hi>Red dragon,</hi> he is a fawning Fox, and a devouring Lyon, his Government is onely in this world, therefore called, <hi>The god of this world,</hi> and he ruleth onely over ſuch men <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 4. Eph. 2. 2. 1 Iohn 3. 8. Ioh. 1. 44 Pſ. 52. 3.</note> as <hi>are in darkneſs,</hi> therefore called, <hi>The ſpirit that now worketh in the children of diſobedience;</hi> and they that (willingly) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſin, are ſaid <hi>to be of the Devil,</hi> therefore wicked men that are his children (like him) love evil more then good, and <hi>delight in lyes more then to ſpeack truth;</hi> he hath alſo many baits to enſnare men, ſometime he propoundeth Honor, ſometime Riches, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time Praiſe and Pleaſure, &amp;c. his mouth was full of this when he came to tempt Chriſt, <hi>All this will I give thee if thou wilt fall down and worſhip me</hi> (or if we will but worſhip God in his way) yea he brings this Scripture too, It is written, ſaith he, thus and thus: When men give way to any temptation of the Devil, they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the truth, and not <hi>receiving the truth in the love of it, is the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Theſſ: 2. 10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>cauſe why God ſendeth ſtrong deluſions to believe lyes,</hi> and are given over to their own luſts; then God ſaith of a man or a nation, as of <hi>Iſrael, Lo-ammi, Ye are not my people, and I will not be your God.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 1. 9</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond cauſe of our diſtempers is, our corrupt nature, which is prone to rceeive all evil from Satan, as the earth the ſeed caſt into it, or the tinder at fire every ſpark; the Devil caſts in the ſeed, corrupt Nature brings forth increaſe, he ſtrikes the flint, and corrupt Nature makes it a flame; corrupt Nature is prone to delight in new things, &amp; Satan always puts fair and ſpecious ſhews upon every error, he caſts them by the mould of truth, but ever addes or adminiſheth, and that he brings under the notion of new truths, for Satan can be (and doubtleſs is at this day) <hi>transformed</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 14. Mat. 24. 24.</note> 
               <hi>into an Angel of light,</hi> and ſo works upon mens fancies, <hi>That if it were poſsible, he ſhould deceive the very Elect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third cauſe is, evil men, Papiſts, Jeſuits, Jews, Libertines, prophane Worldlings, and all other ſeduced Schiſmatical Seducers that hate all Reformation, becauſe they love not the truth;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:161820:10"/> theſe are Satans inſtruments, children of darkneſs, &amp; hate the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of light, they hold counſels againſt them, make conſpiracies, uſe diabolical divinations, pretend propheſies, revelations and miracle; ſome to broach falſe tenents, ſeeming to be zealous for Chriſt, but are his enemies, others to raiſe diſcontents &amp; diſobedience in the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, againſt the powers ordained by God, they invent lyes, ſcandal, and foment jealouſie, to make factions &amp; diviſions both in Church and State, &amp; have influence into great Councels, Societies &amp; Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, yea, into our Victorious Army, where by diviſion they have ſtaggered more, then any power of the ſword could ever have done; theſe are interwoven with us in diſguiſed ſhapes, they are <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> in the extreams, and <hi>Independents</hi> to all looſneſs of liberty and ſlighting of duty, tell you that you are in Chriſt (if you be as they) and cannot ſin, nor ought to pray for pardon, that Chriſt dyed for all equally, for <hi>Judas</hi> as for <hi>Peter;</hi> that Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and the motions of the Spirit (not Scripture) are your Rule to walk by, denying the Morallity of the Law, queſtion whether the ſoul be mortal or immortal; that men have free-wil to repent, and to be ſaved; that the Chriſtian Sacraments are no way neceſſary, and that rebaptizing is lawful and neceſſary; that the Lords day is no more to be obſerved then any other day; that our godly Miniſters are not Miniſters of Chriſt, but their calling An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian, with a hundred more groſs errors, deſtructive to the foundation of true Religion; all which they have ſpirits abroad to infuſe into men, as they finde their natural luſts inclined, by which they have brought confuſion not onely in Counſels, Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties, Cities, and our Victorious Army, but in all families, ſo as we erre, and erre exceedingly, both in judgement and practice: Take it for certain, there are many hundred Jeſuits at this day among us, and have overſpread the whole Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> (I will not believe <hi>Scotland</hi> is free) they are in all places like the frogs of <hi>Egypt,</hi> even in the Saints conventicles (as ſome call them) and it may be in our common pulpits ſometimes; theſe are they that ſpeak evil of Authority, and caſt reproaches upon the Miniſtery, to bring Law and Goſpel into contempt, and to ſet up new lights, and new Government in the world; they ſpread the failings of Parliament abroad to the ears of all countreys, and belye them groſly, make every mole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>il a mountain, ſeem to divine their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:161820:10"/> and belye the very truth, ſet the kingdom in hurliburly, put whole counties to petition in unſeemly maner, to command Requeſts, and to requeſt things not to be granted without ruine, and thereby think to work ruine by the denial, all to hinder ſetle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, reformation and peace, and to bring in Popery in the crowd, among the reſt of their old hereſies newly revived; theſe like <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres,</hi> who withſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> withſtand and reſiſt <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 8.</note> the truth, being armed with all the power and policy of hell and <hi>Rome;</hi> but their great Maſter-piece hath been to break the union between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> as it was <hi>Romes</hi> endeavors for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years to hold them from conjunction, and was no ſmall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartning to them when they became conjoyned: What our brethren will do I know not, I will not prejudge a Kingdom, they have been true, and I hope will be ever, but <hi>Barwick</hi> and <hi>Carliſle</hi> ought not to be held in Gariſon; our Covenant is with God, as well as one with another, and the Kirk to their everlaſting praiſe uphold it, <hi>If it were but a mans covenant, yet if it be confirmed, no</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 15 Lev 26. 25.</note> 
               <hi>man diſanulleth,</hi> but God is a juſt God, and <hi>will avenge the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel of his Covenant</hi> on him that tranſgreſſeth: I would ſay to <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> as <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid to <hi>Lot, Let there be no</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 13. 8.</note> 
               <hi>ſtrife between you, for you are Brethren,</hi> &amp; ſo are your Armies too<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if you jar to blood, you will commit two great evils, you will both fight for your enemies that will deſtroy you both, and you (or one of you) will incur Gods judgements upon your poſterities: I pray remember what the Lord himſelf ſaith, <hi>I will give the men</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 34. 18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>that have tranſgreſſed my Covenant, and have not performed the words of the Covenant which they made before me, when they cut the calf in twain, &amp;c. I will even give them into the hands of their enemies, and into the hands of them that ſeek their life, and they ſhall be meat for the fowls, and for beaſts, &amp;c.</hi> Will you deſtroy your ſelves, becauſe the enemy could not do it? conſider the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that wiſe &amp; able Soldier Sir <hi>Jacob Aſhley,</hi> when Routed and taken near <hi>Stowe,</hi> ſpeaking to Colonel <hi>Morgan,</hi> and to gallant Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor <hi>Hawksworth,</hi> and others, <hi>Gentlemen</hi> (ſaid be) <hi>you may now put up your ſword, for the War is done, we are able to do no more by the power of an Army, except you fall out among your ſelves;</hi> this was a fair warming, he was more our friend in ſpeaking it, then we to our ſelves in contending: Know that this is the Jeſuits
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:161820:11"/> 
               <hi>Maxime, Firſt divide, then conquer:</hi> Hiſtory tells us, <hi>Rome</hi> by this means hath gained more Kingdoms then by the ſword, and this is the deſign at this day.</p>
            <p>Now let <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> ſay as <hi>Joab</hi> ſaid to <hi>Abiſhai, If the Aſſyrians be too ſtrong for me, then thou ſhalt help me, but if</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>am. 10. 11.</note> 
               <hi>the children of Ammon be too ſtrong for thee, I will come and help thee;</hi> thus you have Covenanted, and wo to you if you do it not: Whether one or the other, whilſt united, none can hurt you, once disjoyned, you are both deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>There is yet one cauſe more, and that is God, he is the cauſe of all cauſes: Let the inſtrument be what, or who it will, by which a man, a family, a people or Kingdom is afflicted or deſtroyed, God is the effecient cauſe, men nor devils can do nothing without God; they are but Gods executioners of wrath, and judgement for ſin, but the rod in Gods hand, <hi>Aſſyria is but the rod of Gods anger:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 10. 5.</note> Sickneſs, pain, impriſonment, loſs of goods, war, peſtilence, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and all afflictions whatſover, are from God; to ſome for chaſtiſement, by which <hi>they learn righteouſneſs;</hi> to others as judgements, to puniſh and to deſtroy, <hi>Is there any evil</hi> (ſaith God) <note place="margin">Am. 3. 9</note> 
               <hi>in the city, and I have not done it?</hi> (that is, evil of puniſhment, not evil of ſin) <hi>God forms the light, and creates darkneſs, makes peace,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 45. 7. Iſ. 42 24</note> 
               <hi>and creates war, Who gave Jacob for a ſpoil, and Iſrael to the rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers? did not the Lord, he againſt whom we have ſinned?</hi> when God will puniſh a ſinful people, by the ill Government of Kings and Princes, <hi>He leads away Counſellors ſpoiled, and makes Judges</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob 12. 17</note> 
               <hi>fools;</hi> when <hi>Iſrael</hi> will be hypocrites, to draw near unto God with their mouthes, and remove their hearts far from him, God will make the <hi>wiſdom of the wiſe to periſh, and the underſtanding</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 29. 14.</note> 
               <hi>of the prudent ſhall be hid:</hi> When God will puniſh a King for op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, that King ſhall hearken to evil Councel, and refuſe the good Counſel of grave and wiſe men; ſo did <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> and loſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ten tribes, the text ſaith, <hi>The thing was done of the Lord:</hi> When <note place="margin">1 King. 12. 18 4.</note> God will bring the ſword upon wicked Counſellors, and upon a Nation together, he can make void all the Counſels of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> When <hi>Iſrael deviſed miſchief, and gave wicked Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 19. 7.</note> God turns that wickedneſs to effect his own purpoſe, and by it brings a ſword upon themſelves and the people: <hi>The Princes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 11. ver. 2. 8.</note> 
               <hi>of Zoan became fools, and the Princes of Noph were deceived, that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:161820:11"/> they erred in every work,</hi> the text ſaith, <hi>It was God that mingled</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 19. 13, 14. Iob. 34. 29.</note> 
               <hi>a perverſe ſpirit among them: When God giveth quietneſs</hi> (ſaith holy Job) <hi>who can make trouble? and when he hideth his face, who can behold him? whether it be done againſt a nation, or againſt a man onely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the ſins of an impenitent people provoke God, to bring deſtroying judgements upon that nation, he withdraws his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon reſtraining grace from men, and leaves them to their own luſts (he will puniſh ſin with ſin) wicked men ſhall act according to their own ſeveral luſts, and grow more wicked, oppreſſing, kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and reviling one another, till they be like <hi>Judea</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Vid. Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſep. bel. Jud. lib. 6. &amp; lib. 7</note> deſtroyed one by another, and at laſt made a ſpoil and a prey to the enemy: When a lying ſpirit is put into the mouth of a Miniſtery, as in <hi>Ahabs</hi> 400. prophets, expect ſpeedy ruine and deſolations; or if men and Armies will go againſt the word of God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by the mouth of Gods meſſengers, they are not likely to proſper, but like <hi>Ahab</hi> miſcarry in their confidence; but to all that are godly, and of upright hearts, I ſay with the Prophet, <hi>Fear</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 45. 4.</note> 
               <hi>not, be ſtrong, behold your God will come with vengeance, even God, with a recompence he will come and ſave you:</hi> This is the time of Gods indignation, he will puniſh the <hi>Inhabitants of the earth for their iniquity, the earth ſhall alſo diſcloſe her bloods, and ſhall no more cover her ſlain, it will be but for a moment</hi> (the time is appointed by God) <hi>and the indignation ſhall be overpaſt: Believe in the Lord</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 20. 20.</note> 
               <hi>your God, ſo ſhall you be eſtabliſhed; believe his Prophets, ſo ſhall you proſper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God (now in ſpecial maner) calls his people to humiliation, to repentance, and reformation of ſin; when Gods hand was upon whole <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the days of <hi>David,</hi> he enquired the cauſe (he knew it was for ſin, for God onely puniſheth for ſin) and the Lord revealed to him that it was <hi>for Saul and his bloody houſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 21. 1.</note> 
               <hi>he ſlew ſome of the Gibeonites,</hi> contrary to Covenant; it was many generations before <hi>Sauls</hi> time, that <hi>Joſhua</hi> and the Princes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had made a covenant with the <hi>Gibeonites, Saul</hi> ſwore not to it, and <hi>Joſhua</hi> was forbid to make any league with them, yea, the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> engaged <hi>Joſhua</hi> and the Princes by craft; and further, the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſware not unto it, but after three days (when their craft was diſcovered) murmured becauſe of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:161820:12"/> Oath; not withſtanding all this, <hi>Joſhua</hi> durſt not make <hi>null</hi> that Covenant; And why? <hi>Leaſt</hi> (faith he) <hi>wrath be upon us becauſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua chap. 9. 8</note> 
               <hi>of the oath,</hi> not ſo much as put one of them to death, who had by craft deceived them.</p>
            <p>We know when our Enemies were ſtrong, and we very weak, the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> invited the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> to our aſſiſtance, they as wilingly came, but deſired a perfect union of both Kingdoms, and to that end a Solemn League and Covenant was entred into by both, and joyfully received, not onely ſworn unto by our Nobles, Knights and Gentlemen, but generally by all the people (or by ſinful negligence omitted) the command is war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable by Scripture, <hi>Whoſoever would not Covenant to ſeek the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 15. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, ſhould be put to death, whether ſmall or great:</hi> In our Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant we ſwear <hi>Reformation, Eccleſiaſtical, and Perſonal defence of Religion againſt the common Enemy, Reformation in Religion, in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>according to Gods word, and the beſt Reformed Churches: And we have ſworn (every one for himſelf) to endeavor the neareſt conjunction that can be in the three Kingdoms in Religion, Form of Government, Directory of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> &amp;c. as ſhall be found moſt conſonant with Scripture, not as it is eſtabliſhed in <hi>Scotland,</hi> or any other Reformed Church, except in tryal they be found the beſt; and herein the Kingdom of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is to alter (as well as <hi>England)</hi> any thing not fully agreeing with Gods Word: Now he that hath not endeavored this, and doth not ſtill endeavor it, hath broken his Covenant; but ſuch as have oppoſed it (let their pretence be what it will) are guilty of perjury before the high and holy God.</p>
            <p>2. We have ſworn to <hi>endeavor to extirpate Popery, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy, and Church Government by Prelavical Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and alſo to extirpate Superſtition, Hereſie, Schiſm, Prophaneneſs, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is contrary to ſound Doctrine, and the power of godlineſs:</hi> Therefore, he or they who look back to Popery, or that endeavor not to the uttermoſt to aboliſh all Popiſh Superſtition, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, Hereſie, Schiſms and Blaſphemy, violate their Oath; but they that endeavor to ſupport either Popery, Prelacy, Hereſie or Schiſm, are injurious to God, to his Truth, and to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and of ſuch God will ſurely avenge his Covenant.</p>
            <p>3. We have ſworn to endeavor <hi>with our Eſtates and Lives
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:161820:12"/> (every one for himſelf) mutually to preſerve the Rights and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of Parliaments, and the Liberties of the Kingdom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> Conſider, how many among us may be taxed in this particular, for falſe ſwearing and for prefidious perſons; 1. They that endeavor not to aſſiſt the Preſervation of Parliament Priviledges: 2. They that make breaches, and joyn with them that do, as too many have done, of Soldiers, Apprentices of City and Countrey: 3. The Liberty of the Subject, which many for Self-intereſt infringed; this latter we know is involved in the former: 4. They that ſhall or have endeavored to bring His Majeſty to the ſole rule of the Kingdom, till aſſurance be given to the Parliament, of the Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Religion, and of the Subjects Liberty for future, are Covenant-breakers, and may be deemed as enemies to poſterity; but ſecurity once given to the Parliament, God forbid that Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or people ſhould deſire to diminiſh any thing in His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties juſt power and greatneſs.</p>
            <p>4. We ſwore, that we wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>endeavor that all Incendiaries, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants, evil Inſtruments, that hinder Reformation of Religion, divide the King from His People, or one of the Kingdoms from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, or that make Factions and Parties among the People, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Covenant, may be brought to condign puniſhment, &amp;c.</hi> What ſhall we ſay or think of this, when any one Kingdom ſhall not onely not bring to puniſhment ſuch perſons, but connive at them, and ſuffer them among them, though they are, and have been known Enemies and Incendiaries, Hinderers of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Dividers between both Kingdoms, to ſet them together in blood, and that make Factions and Parties among the People, contrary to the Covenant, Is not this a breach of the Covenant, and diſhonor to the moſt high God before whom we have ſworn?</p>
            <p>5. We have acknowledged it a great mercy and bleſſing, that the Peace is concluded and ſettled between the two Kingdoms (ſuch as God denyed to our Progenitors) and therefore ſwore to <hi>endeavor, the two Kingdoms may remain conjoyned in a firm Peace and Union to all Poſterities, and that Juſtice may be done upon the wilful oppoſers thereof,</hi> if ſo, Who dare break this Union, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Kingdom (without perjury) can attempt a War, or draw a ſword againſt the other, except firſt he were ſet upon, and that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:161820:13"/> no pacification could be made (and I hope neither Kingdom will blame me for what I write) I have entred into the ſame Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and am bound by my Covenant to endeavor the Peace and Union, though it prove my prejudice, 'tis my duty, which to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect were to incur Gods diſpleaſure, and juſt judgement upon my ſelf.</p>
            <p>6. We did ſwear, <hi>In this common cauſe of Religion, Liberty, and peace of the Kingdoms, to aſsiſt and defend all that entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Covenant, in purſuance thereof, and not to ſuffer our ſelves by perſwaſion or terror, to be divided or drawn from this conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor to be neuters in this cauſe, but to continue in it all the days of our lives againſt all oppoſition:</hi> Now let every man, and both Kingdoms lay it to heart, and conſider how baſe and cowardly they have been (I mean not all) to own this Covenant, and to act according as they have ſworn, I utter it with grief; I know many that have taken it, are quite fallen from it, ſome to the left hand, ſome to the right hand; all w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>h God ſees, and will once exact an accompt of every man, <hi>For God is not mocked;</hi> deceive not your ſelves, Gods Honor and Juſtice is ingaged in it, <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 10. 3</note> 
               <hi>ſhall ſpring up</hi> (upon them) <hi>as hemlock in the furrows of the field, that have ſworn falſly in making a Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I finde recorded in the <hi>Turkiſh Hiſtory</hi> a remarkable ſtory, That after a long War betwen <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, (but a Papiſt) and <hi>Amurath</hi> Emperor of <hi>Turky, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſlaus</hi> made a Pea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e with <hi>Amurath,</hi> and entred into a Covenant, which was interchangeably given in writing; but the King of <hi>Hungary</hi> was perſwaded by <hi>Julian</hi> a Cardinal, to violate that Covenant, which he did, and at great advantage, ſecretly and ſpeedily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared a mighty Army, and fell upon the Turks territories; the Emperor of <hi>Turky</hi> hearing of it, as ſoon as he could, prepared to oppoſe him, they came to a field hatrel, and the Turks loſt many men, ſo that the Emperor and his whole Army were in danger, at laſt the Emperor ſeeing a Crucifix in one of the King of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garies</hi> Banners, he pluckt forth of his boſom the Writing and Covenant which he had received from the King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and holding it up in his hand, with his eyes caſt up to heaven, ſaid theſe words <hi>(Behold thou crucified Chriſt, is this the League thy Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in thy name made with me which they have without cauſe vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated?
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:161820:13"/> if thou be a God, as they ſay thou art, revenge the wrong done unto thy name, and to me, and ſhew thy power upon thy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulious people, who in their deeds deny thee their God:</hi> This ſaid, the battel grew fierce on both ſides, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſlaus</hi> was wholly and totally routed, himſelf ſlain by a <hi>Janizary,</hi> and great numbers of the Chriſtians ſlaughtered: Conſider this example, <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland:</hi> and as Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>Remember Lots wife;</hi> So ſay I, Remember <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſlaus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tiſſaphernes,</hi> Lieutenant to the King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> broke a truce which he made with the <hi>Grecians;</hi> the <hi>Grecians</hi> ſent him thanks by his own Herald, ſaying, he had thereby engaged the gods, in whoſe name the truce was ſworn, to be on their ſide: <hi>Cleome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> King of <hi>Lacedemonia</hi> made a truce with the <hi>Argians</hi> for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven days, but did it with deceitful equivocation, meaning to take advantage of the night; And ſo did, for the third night when the <hi>Argians</hi> were ſecure, and aſleep, he fell upon them, and was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards beaten, and his Army ſcattered by the women of the City of <hi>Argos,</hi> in revenge of their husbands that he had trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly ſlain, and after this, <hi>Cleomenes</hi> kild himſelf with a knife.</p>
            <p>It would be great happineſs, if <hi>England</hi> would enquire as holy <hi>David</hi> did, wheter Gods hand now againſt us, be not for our breach of Covenant, (though not National, for I hope bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but as to particular men it is manifeſt) Conſider, I pray, why is it that the common people of <hi>England</hi> riſe up tumultuouſly againſt Authority, and Priviledges of Parliament, contrary to their Covenant? is it not a juſt Judgement from God, becauſe Authority have been remiſs in their Covenant, and many have ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely broken it with God; therefore God ſuffereth a Covenant-breaking people to break Covenant with them, now tumultuouſly riſen againſt them in <hi>ESSEX, S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RREY, KENT,</hi> &amp;c. that God may deſtroy the one by the other: If it be ſo, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns every man to humble himſelf before God, renew his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and in the ſtrength of the Almighty, to reſolve to keep it to the death: or let it be done to the perſiſters in breaking, as to the ſeven Sons of <hi>Saul;</hi> for if we ſuffer the Covenant to be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, <hi>We cannot proſper, nor ſhall we be delivered:</hi> Beſides conſider, <note place="margin">Ezek. 17. 15. Iſa. 26. 9.</note> we are not onely reformed, <hi>Nor have learned righteouſneſs, though Gods judgements</hi> are in the earth, and upon our ſelves; but
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:161820:14"/> are grown more impious in finning then before; I will Inſtance in ten particulars, for God which is now in controverſie with us.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Pride; pride of the inward man, or of the outward man, is a ſin tranſcendent to what it hath been, witneſs mens and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens high conceits of themſelves, boaſtings of gifts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Their high looks, antick geſtures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Their new invented faſhions, rich Clothes, painted and ſpotted Faces, coſtly Coaches, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty Purſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Pride we know is a ſin of <hi>Sodom,</hi> God hates it, makes war againſt it, <hi>He reſiſts the proud,</hi> therefore ſaith, <hi>He</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iam. 4. 6. Ier. 13. 9 2 Chro. 32. 25.</note> 
               <hi>will mar the pride of Judah, and the great pride of Jeruſalem:</hi> God ſaith, for the pride of the women, <hi>the men ſhall ſalt by the ſword, and mighty men in the war, the pride of Hezekiahs heare cauſed wrath upon all Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Covetouſneſs; This is a ſin no leſs hateful to God, then hurtful to men; but never more evidently ſeen to rage in men, then at this day: Witneſs men in places of truſt in the Common-weal, ſee if (as the Prophet ſaith) <hi>From the leaſt to the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 6 13</note> 
               <hi>greateſt, every one be not given to covetouſneſs;</hi> Covetouſneſs is a ſin that excludes men <hi>from the Kingdom of Heaven</hi> when they dye, <note place="margin">Eph 5. 15 Ier. 8. 10. 1 Tim. 6. 10.</note> and covetous men are burthens to the earth while they live, <hi>The love of money cauſeth men to erre from the faith, and pierce them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves through with many ſorrows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Oppreſſion; This ſin and the fear of God are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite, they dwell not together in one Kingdom, <hi>Thou ſhalt not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Levit. 25. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> 
               <hi>oppreſs, but thou ſhalt fear thy God;</hi> Where the fear of God is, there is no oppreſſion; where oppreſſion is, there is no fear of God: Oppreſſors are in Scripture ſet forth by nature and names of cruel Beaſts, <hi>Bulls, Bears, Wolves, Dogs, Kine of Baſhan,</hi> &amp;c. Now let me appeal to all men, if there were ever more beaſts of this kinde in this Kingdom, <hi>Are there not ſound amongſt us wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 6. 26, 27, 28.</note> 
               <hi>men that lay wait as he that ſetteth ſnares: they ſet a traps they catch men, their houſes are full of deceit, they are become greats and waxen rich,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Robbery is a ſin abounding in <hi>England,</hi> open and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Robberies are committed and connived at; many more have been Executed for Robbing then now, but never ſo many Robbers as now; they that will crucifie <hi>Chriſt,</hi> will ſet <hi>Barra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> free; there are men not onely like the men of <hi>Shechem,</hi> liers in wait
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:161820:14"/> in the mountains, but thoſe that rob the Kingdom by a kinde of Toleration, yea, that rob the poor and the fatherleſs, <hi>That turn</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 10. 2.</note> 
               <hi>the needy from judgement, that widows may be their prey;</hi> yea, they will be found to be robbers of Gods people diſtreſſed in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſome will even <hi>rob God himſelf.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3. 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>5. Murther; This is a crying ſin, it cryed to Heaven againſt us, before our great afflictions came upon us, and now it cryes double as much as before; it call'd the Sword upon us, and the Sword hath increaſed our guilt: God ſtirred up the <hi>Caldeans, Syrians, Moabites,</hi> and children of <hi>Ammon</hi> againſt <hi>Jeboiakim,</hi> to avenge the blood that <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> had ſhed in his days; the blood of <hi>Rochel,</hi> and of <hi>Germany,</hi> ſtill cryes againſt <hi>England,</hi> and the blood of <hi>Ireland</hi> will not be ſatisfied, but blood for blood: <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> once bled by Maſſacre, now bleeds by flattery; we feed them with words, but deſtroy them by withholding actions; the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders for Self intereſt, and unjuſt Stewards in <hi>England,</hi> are the ſlaughtermen of conſumed <hi>Ireland:</hi> Not to ſave, is to kill, this is not to cleanſe the Land of blood, but to make it more bloody; we would not endure to be ſo dealt with.</p>
            <p>6. Exceſs; In eating and drinking to gluttony and drunkenneſs, it hath long been <hi>Englands</hi> ſin, but is now greatly aggravated by the circumſtance of time; God by his great ſcourge calls us to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, <hi>To faſting, and to weeping, but behold feaſting and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 22. 19.</note> 
               <hi>wine in bowls, lie upon beds of ivory, invent inſtruments of muſick, eat the lambs out of the flock, and the calves out of the midſt of the ſtall,</hi> for this cauſe God ſaid, <hi>He hated the excellency</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Amos 6. 4, 5, 6. Verſ. 8.</note> 
               <hi>of Jacob, and abhorred his pallaces,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>Therefore will I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver up the City, and all that is therein:</hi> God may as juſtly deal ſo with us, and will if we reform not, <hi>And lay to heart the afflictions of Joſeph,</hi> and relieve the objects of pity, every hour before us, who have loſt all, but they give nothing that have gained much.</p>
            <p>7. Whoredom; A ſin puniſhed by death by Gods Law, and the ſinner ſhut <hi>out from heaven</hi> by Chriſts Goſpel, but in <hi>England</hi> neither puniſhed, nor excluded from the ſeat of Juſtice at this time; he is counted gallant company, that will whore, and boaſt of it when he hath done; remember <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Coſbi,</hi> that ſin coſt <note place="margin">Num. 25 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> twenty four thouſand lives, themſelves alſo ſlain for that ſin by <hi>Phinehas.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:161820:15"/>
            <p>8. Prophanation of the Lords day; A ſin of which this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom hath been much guilty in many parts of it, and is at this day, by doing the works of our calling, uſing ſports, and recreations for pleaſure, idle ſpeaking, and omiſſion of holy worſhip, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the precept, <hi>Thou ſhalt not do thine own work, nor ſpeak</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 58. 13.</note> 
               <hi>thine own words, but ſhalt honor God wholly on that day.</hi> But of late days men are ſo impious, that they deny the Command to keep it holy, as if God had neither appointed a time for publique worſhip, nor required any worſhip of us, but after our own wills.</p>
            <p>9. Contempt of the Miniſtery; What oppoſition corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath made againſt the Miniſtery, we know in all times; but when, or in what Kingdom was it ever more oppoſed then now? except in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> till <hi>Gods wrath aroſe againſt them without</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 36. 16.</note> 
               <hi>remedy,</hi> and in <hi>Germany</hi> (a little before the deſolation of that Monarchy) by the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> who have been cheriſhed in <hi>England</hi> for ſuch a purpoſe: Thoſe Miniſters by whoſe Miniſtery they were converted (if converted at all) are by them contemned and deſpiſed, their Miniſtery abhorred as old truths, common things, nothing but new errors and hereſies will ſerve them; theſe men do but their kinde, and I complain not ſo much of them, as that they are ſuffered to diſturb a Commonweal, and be a ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling block to weak Chriſtians (I mean not ſuch as onely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in matter of Ceremony or Circumſtance, but ſuch as erre in Doctrine) ſome are to be caſt out according to the Apoſtles rule, by excommunication, that is, ſuch as are Church members; There are others, ſuch as are not properly Church members, yet live within the pale of the Church, turbulent to the State, and the peace of the Kingdom, that ſeduce ſouls to er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and to rebellion, under the notion of Religion; theſe are to be dealt with by the Civil Magiſtrate, and that ſharply, <hi>I would</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 12.</note> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>they were even cut off that trouble you;</hi> he means not by Excommunication, for that he and the Church had power to have done, but not to puniſh as a Magiſtrate ought in ſuch a caſe: The Prophet that did ſeduce any to falſe Worſhip, was by the Law <hi>put to death,</hi> not by <hi>Aaron,</hi> but by <hi>Moſes; If</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 13. 5. Verſ. 9.</note> 
               <hi>any Brother, Son, Siſter, Wife, Friend, &amp;c. ſhould intice any man to falſe Worſhip, he or they was to be put to death without pity:</hi> I ſay
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:161820:15"/> not that error nor all hereſie is to be puniſhed with death, though all to be ſuppreſſed by penal Laws, and puniſhed according to the offence and nature: The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> urging the duty of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to the Magiſtrate, ſaith, <hi>It is the will of God</hi> to ſubmit; he means not Thieves, Murtherers, Blaſphemers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but Chriſtians within the Church, ſuch as Chriſt had made free, therefore he ſaith, <hi>As free, and not uſing your liberty as a cloak of maliciouſneſs.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 13, 14, 15</note> There is a liberty left in matter of Diſcipline, but no liberty given to particular men to repugn that Diſcipline that is eſtabliſhed by the Magiſtrate, not diſagreeing from Gods word, much more in matter of Doctrine, nor do I ſay, any particular man doubting ſhall be compelled or puniſhed, but exhorted from day to day, except he labor to draw others, and thereby the peace of the Church and State be diſquieted; if ſo, ſuch ought to be curb'd by the ſword of the Magiſtrate, and this cannot be ſaid, is to puniſh for conſcience, nor for opinion, but for turbulency.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>Thyatira</hi> is reproved for ſuffering that woman <hi>Jezabel,</hi> that called her ſelf a Propheteſs, to ſeduce the people to error: <hi>Pergamos</hi> for ſuffering erroneous Doctrine, is threatned ſharply; The error of the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> cauſed God to depart and to remove the Candleſtick from them; <hi>Rome</hi> once Chriſtian, by permitting one error then error begetting error, ſhe became Antchriſtian: There is a propinquity between error and error, and between error and hereſie; one uſhereth in the other, and a multitude followeth at their heels, experience ſhews it and we know (except any be wilfull igno ant) that our preſent errors and diverſity of opinions, have been ſpread by the ſubtilty of the common enemy, whileſt they have united themſelves againſt us, and is their ſole refuge and ground of their confidence, that by which they have divided the Parliament among themſelves, loſt the peoples affections to them, alienated one friend from another, and made one man jealous of another, that we are grown to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and ſcattered as a people without a head, like ſheep with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſhepherd.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, The ſin of Self-love, a known iniquity of all times, and mother of Miſchief, now a deſtroying ſin in this Kingdom, I may ſay of three Kigdoms, all lying upon the bed of languiſhing; it is a ſweet ſin, whileſt the ſinner pleaſeth himſelf in it, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>fills the mouth with gravel:</hi> it produceth moſt bitter fruits, <note place="margin">Prov. 20. 17.</note>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:161820:16"/> like that which <hi>Eve</hi> eat in the garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> kills all; Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love is ſaid to be blinde, it ſees not to Judge it ſelf and in Judging others is always partial; How then can it be well when ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovers judge all things? <hi>If any man</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>will follow me, let him deny himſelf;</hi> he that denies not himſelf cannot be Chriſts <note place="margin">Mat. 16. 24. Mark 8. 34.</note> Diſciple, and he that is not Chriſts Diſciple, is not one of his members therefore cannot be a good Member of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weal; other Members may dye, the body be ſick, but he knows it not, he owns it not: As was ſaid of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> ſo may be ſaid of <hi>England Gray hairs are here and there upon him, yet he knows it</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 7 9.</note> 
               <hi>not; Self-love and ſelf-intereſt hath devoured his ſtrength,</hi> and he is brought to the laſt gaſp.</p>
            <p>The remedy is clear, if the forenamed ſins be the cauſe; take <note place="margin">Pſ. 25. 10. Iſa. 57. 15</note> away the cauſe, and the effect will ceaſe: Keep thy Covenant with God and man conſcionably, Extirpate Pride, and plant Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility <note place="margin">Iſa. 58. 6.</note> in the room, Hate covetouſneſs, Do good to all, Oppreſs none, Looſe the bands of wickedneſs, Undo the heavy burthens, and let the oppreſſed go free, Take nothing from any man; if <note place="margin">Luke 19. 8. &amp; 3. 14. Pſ 51. 14</note> you have taken any thing falſly, reſtore it as <hi>Zacheus</hi> did; Let the Soldier offer violence to none, neither to Law, nor to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but be content with wages; Seek pardon from heaven for Blood guiltineſs, redeem the time paſt by vigilance, and double endeavors for time to come, to preſerve the lives of them yet living, eſpecially thoſe in <hi>Joſephs</hi> afflictions, now in jeopardy in <hi>Ireland;</hi> Be temperate in the uſe of all Gods creatures; uſe every <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5. 6. Eph. 5. 18 Pro 2. 16 1 Theſſ. 5. 22.</note> thing with ſobriety, moderation and thankſgiving; Let not that which God gave to chear the heart, deſtroy the ſoul; Keep thy ſelf from the evil woman, from the flattering of the tongue of the ſtrange woman; Abſtain from all fleſhly luſts, and from all appearances of evil; Worſhip God in Spirit and in Truth, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie his Sabbath, and ſanctifie your days of Humiliation; Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your ſelves, &amp; afflict your ſouls, they are days of atonement and <note place="margin">Lev. 23. 27.</note> Reconciliation, then make them not formal onely, as mock-Faſts, but holy convocations, reverence Gods Miniſters, ſent of God with <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 5. 13. Mat. 10. 41. Mark 8. 34.</note> tidings of peace, Honor them for their Office, and for their works ſake, as thoſe that labor &amp; watch for your ſouls; Receive a Prophet in the name of a Prophet, and you ſhall have a Prophets reward; Deny thy ſelf, take up the croſs, and follow Chriſt: Happy were
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:161820:16"/> it if all that are in Authority would deny themſelves in action, as in words, Deny their profits, their ſelf-honor, and all ſelf-inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, <note place="margin">Pro. 13. 10.</note> and ſeek the publike good; by pride comes contention, and ſelf-intereſt cauſeth quarrels, humble your ſelves before God, and <note place="margin">1 Pe. 5. 6.</note> he will exalt you: but if you ſeek honor, it will fly from you; God will honor them that honor him: Conſider this promiſe, <note place="margin">1 Sam. 2. 30.</note> 
               <hi>If my people which are called by my name ſhall humble themſelves, and pray &amp; ſeek my face, and turn from their wicked ways, then will</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 7. 14. Pro. 16. 7.</note> 
               <hi>I hear in heaven, and will forgive their ſin, and will heal their land: when a mans ways pleaſe the Lord, he makes even his enemies to be at peace with him:</hi> This is the ſure &amp; never-failing healing Plaiſter; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it, ye Phyſicians, &amp; heal the Kingdoms before they be paſt cure.</p>
            <p>In the next place, becauſe there is a Diſeaſe that men call <hi>The Kings Evil,</hi> which they ſay none can heal but the King; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe His Majeſty hath offered ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to it, let Addreſſes be made unto Him again and again, in the Name of three diſeaſed Kingdoms: <hi>In the morning</hi> (ſaith the Wiſe man) ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> thy ſeed, <note place="margin">Eccle. 11. 6.</note> 
               <hi>and in the evening withhold not thine hand; for thou knoweſt not whether ſhall proſper; this or that &amp;c.</hi> All bleſſings are from God, <hi>The Kings heart is in the hand of the Lord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 21. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>ſoever he will:</hi> If Kings have a gift to heal, <hi>Kings being nurſing-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to their People,</hi> you that are Phyſicians, that cannot agree upon the cure, humbly ſupplicate to the King for a touch: if he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, tell his people, to ſecure juſt Rights, for people choſe Kings to defend them, to maintain their Rights, and to heal their ſores, not to deſtroy them, or infringe their Liberties, nor to hurt them any way, againſt which Parliaments are the peoples ſecurity, and may not be prejudiced: If the King ſecure the peoples Rights, and the people and A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>my obey the Parliament, the work is ended: but ſores neglected often ulcer, and become incurable. Adde hereunto, the change of countrey, Committees, tyrannical as <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raohs</hi> Taskmaſters over the people, that create Malignants, as Pick-pockets make Tumults: ſo long as Oppreſſion is kept up, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections and Rebellions cannot be kept down: The Wiſe-man ſaith, <hi>For the tranſgr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>sion of a Land, many a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the Princes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 2. Chap. 28. 15.</note> 
               <hi>As a roaring Lyon and a raging Hart, ſo is a wicked Ruler over the people:</hi> Many Rulers is a burthen, and one roaring Lyon is fearful; caſe the one, and take heed of the other, leſt we be torn
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:161820:17"/> in pieces, and there be none to deliver us: <hi>A Lyon hath roared,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Amo. 3. 8</note> 
               <hi>who will not fear? the Lord God hath ſpoken, who can but propheſie? There is a time to kill, and a time to heal, a time to break down, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 3. 3. Eccl. 8. 6.</note> 
               <hi>a time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> And becauſe to every purpoſe there is a time,</hi> (man not knowing that time, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>iſſeth it) <hi>therefore the miſery of m<note place="margin">Eccele. 9 12.</note>n in great upon the earth: And the ſons of men are ſnared in an</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccle. 9 12.</note> 
               <hi>evil time, when it falleth ſuddenly upon them as fiſhes that are taken in an evil net, and birds that are caught in a ſnare:</hi> As men, ſo Monarchies and Kingdoms have their ebbes and flows, and their periods too. God hath appointed their times of change, and the means of their ruine; <hi>He increaſeth the Nations, and deſtroyeth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob 12. 23.</note> 
               <hi>them; he inlargeth the Nations, and ſtraitneth them again. At what inſtant I ſhall ſpeak concerning a Nation, to pull down and to deſtroy it, if that Nation turn from their evil, I will repent of the evil that I thought to do unto them: And at what inſtant I ſhall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 18. 7. 8, 9, 10</note> 
               <hi>ſpeak concerning a Nation, to build and to plant it, if that Nation do evil in my ſight, and obey not my voyce. I will repent of the good wherewith I ſaid I would benefit them:</hi> Yet let not him that put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on his Armor boaſt, for the battel is not to the ſtrong, nor the race to the ſwift.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
